today we're gonna play around with
illustrators type effects to build a
vintage style logo design
modern logo designs tend to be quite
minimalist with a single icon graphic
called word mark but this classic style
is still popular when used for t-shirt
designs or certain hipster brands since
this design is almost entirely type
based it's important to have a good
selection of fonts to work with there's
a good selection of free fonts out there
but they tend to be for personal use
only
i'll be using three typefaces i've just
picked up from a fontsbundle that's
currently on sale if you're watching
this video within a week of it going
live the fonts deal is still available
so if you fancy grabbing these premium
fonts yourself along with a load of
others with a 99 discount check out the
link in the description
so it's been making this vintage style
logo design open up adobe illustrator
and create a new document i'm just
working in a standard a4 art board with
pixel units in the rgb color mode
select the type tool and lay out your
font choices in some empty space i'm
using three fonts from that bundle i've
just mentioned named town 10 black
montebello script and urw din condensed
all three of these fonts have a classic
style to them that reflects the
lettering style of those old logos from
the early 20th century
a combination of heavy geometric sans
series a nice flowing script and a
narrow industrial sansa reef all
complement each other really well
with the selection tool active hold the
alt key and drag a copy of town 10. i'll
show you how to create my design for
spoon graphics in this tutorial so edit
the contents of this first type element
to spoon
click the make envelope button in the
top toolbar then change the drop down to
arc with a bend of 10
these basic text effects are the key
ingredient of vintage style designs they
mimic the lettering styles of those old
handmade logos
hold the alt key and make a duplicate of
the montebello script font change the
wording to graphics then hold the shift
key and click the spoon text element to
add them both to the selection
click the horizontal align center button
in the align panel to center them up
scale the graphics word down while
holding the shift and alt keys to keep
it in proportion and scaling centrally
then nudge it into place with the cursor
keys
make another copy of the geometric sans
town 10 font and edit the contents to
say design blog increase the tracking to
400 in the character panel
add one of the other type elements to
the selection by clicking while holding
the shift key then give the element an
extra click to make it the key object
when you click the align button the key
object won't move out of place
add an arc envelope distort to this
design blog text but this time with
minus 10 so it bends in the other
direction
make a copy of the script font and edit
the contents to the word the
select the rectangle tool and draw a
small square on the artboard holding the
shift key to keep the sides equal
switch the fill over to a stroke in the
toolbar then increase the stroke weight
to three points with the round corners
option checked
switch back to the selection tool and
click and drag near the corner handle to
rotate it by 45 degrees holding the
shift key to keep the angles constrained
go to object transform and scale then
change the vertical value under the
non-uniform option to 50 to squash this
diamond shape
align this shape up by adding an
existing text element to the selection
make the element the key object with an
extra click then press the horizontal
align center button
merge this shape into place vertically
to sit on top of the design with roughly
the same spacing as the other text
elements
scale and position the word into place
to fit within the diamond shape give it
an envelope effect this time using the
rise option from the drop down with a 10
bend
alongside the main brand name vintage
logos also tend to have additional tag
lines and other bits of information
make another copy of the script font and
change the wording to made in positioned
underneath the logo
align it centrally with the other
elements then scale it down slightly
holding the alt and shift keys to keep
it lined up
make another copy of the town 10 font
enter great britain as the wording
spread over two lines and set to the
center aligned paragraph style then
adjust the line height to tighten the
spacing up
apply a quick envelope distort effect
then made in text using the 10 arc
setting to decorate it slightly
make a copy of the urw din font in order
to lay out the shorthand wording estd
for established not edtd like my typo
you can see on screen
split the letters over two lines and
tighten up the leading to align the
characters set the cursor before the
letter t
then use the alt and right cursor key to
adjust the kerning to line up the
letters along their left edges
scale the full text element to the same
height as the great britain wording then
position it off to the left
make a copy of this din text element for
the other side then edit the wording to
2007 which was the date my spoon
graphics blog was set up keep this split
over two lines
add both these din text elements to the
selection and make a group grouping them
together will allow you to line them up
centrally while maintaining the gap
between them
find the star shape from under the
rectangle tool menu and draw a little
decorative shape
position it above the din text and make
a copy for the other side
add a couple more decorative text
elements using the montebello script
using the words tutorials and resources
align them to either side of the diamond
shape make copies of the little star
graphics and add them as embellishments
to these text elements
draw selections around all these
elements then go to object envelope
distort make with warp
choose the arc setting at ten percent
the logo looks great but we can add some
more decorative features to turn it into
a badge style graphic
select the polygon tool and draw a
hexagon on the artboard
clear out the fill and add a black
stroke then scale it up and position it
centrally around the logo elements
bump up the stroke weight to 8 points
then go to effect stylize round corners
enter 10 pixels
squash the hexagon down in size from the
top handle while holding the alt key
till the bottom edge is adjusted by the
same amount
make a copy of the star graphic and
scale it up slightly in some empty space
on the artboard
drag off a copy of this larger shape to
one side then with them both selected
head to object blend and make
select the hexagon outline and go to
object path offset path enter 20 pixels
in the options
hold the shift key and add the stars to
the selection then go to object blend
and replace spine
these star graphics don't quite run all
the way around the shape to fix this
grab the scissors tool and snip the
hexagon at the top point
head back to object blend and blend
options and adjust the settings to
specified steps
check the preview option and adjust the
figure to produce a nice spread of stars
around the logo 41 creates a symmetrical
layout in my example
draw a selection around the entire logo
and hold the alt key to drag a duplicate
off to one side
select all the original elements again
then head to object and expand
appearance and object expand to
permanently set all the fonts strokes
and envelope effects
click the unite button from the
pathfinder panel to merge everything
into one element
this final version is completely made of
vector shapes so it's totally safe to
scale up and down for other users and
export for print
we can also add some finishing touches
over in photoshop to give the design the
popular aged look that works perfectly
with these vintage style designs
copy the logo graphic and create a new
photoshop document now chances are the
scaling will be quite small so enlarge
the canvas with the crop tool before
pasting and scaling the logo
right click on the logo layer and select
convert to smart object
begin with a median effect from the
filter and noise menu
enter a low figure of around 5 pixels to
subtly round off all the corners to
produce a letterpress style stamp effect
go to filter distort and ripple and
reduce the amount to around 20 to add a
subtle bleed effect to the logo
a final cocktail of filters will add
some great texture into the logo to
finish off the vintage print effect
head to filter and select filter gallery
begin with a reticulation effect from
under the sketch menu configure the
settings to 4800
click the new icon at the bottom of the
window to layer up another effect select
torn edges
configure these settings to 37 1 and 17.
play around with the top slider to
adjust the amount of texturing this
filter will produce
a final subtle addition that finishes
off the realistic letterpress style
print effect is an inner glow to remove
this texturing from the edges which
replicates how the ink is spread on a
stamped print
double click the layer to apply an inner
glow layer style configure the settings
to normal black 100 opacity zero choke
then alter the size option to around 24
pixels or whatever suits the scale of
the logo without losing the texturing on
the smaller parts of the design
so i hope you enjoyed this tutorial and
find these tips and techniques useful
for creating your own vintage style logo
designs
if you really love this spoon graphics
design check out the link below to my
t-shirt store if you want to own it for
real
don't forget to subscribe if you want to
be the first to see all my upcoming
tutorials and as always thank you very
much for watching